all right
hey folks you caught me off guard
welcome back to the dark horse podcast
the 40th live stream this is the q and a
section where we engage the questions
with
answers hopefully we can match them up
well enough that they will satisfy
one of our cats has come to love these
live streams because
now for the second time we have fed him
some cream behind you so that we get
a little bit of cap behind you on the
screen we did no such thing that was you
you are a sucker and you have
and i have no idea why he thinks i'm his
mother you are yes
i have some idea yes all right
uh we're gonna start with four questions
from
episode uh 39 and then move on to the
ones from
last hour and then this hour why
are the citizens of portland accepting
such terrible leadership could this be a
test case for unity 2020
at the local level um this is a really
good question
i thought so i think the people of
portland are accepting such
terrible leadership because
people are hell-bent on signaling
their priorities their values
their virtue in the public context and
they have no
understanding of what i have called the
personal responsibility vortex which is
to say
if you instantiate your values directly
in your own life or in your own city you
may be doing so
to the long-term large-scale detriment
of those
very values and so in some sense
portland needs to demand high quality
leadership which involves doing what's
right for portland even when it doesn't
perfectly match the
aspirations of portlanders in other
words you have to get there so
homelessness is a lovely example of this
um lovely in the game theoretic sense
it's a
terrible tragedy but the fact is
um the solutions to homelessness which
we absolutely
should have as a society there's really
no defense of our
failure to deal with people who've
fallen off the bottom of the economic
ladder or uh you know for whatever
reason
but you can't solve it at the city level
and if you try you will make the problem
worse and so portland
because everybody understands that they
want a solution imagines that you can
enact it at any
level so i would just point out this is
uh the same failure we see in
the blm movement which effectively is
advocating
for reparations in all interactions that
anytime there's an interaction
there should be a flow of well-being
from one party to another
you you can't do it that way you can't
do it in a classroom
you can't do it uh in a court there's
certain places that if
you were going to engage in reparations
you could do it that would fairly
distribute
uh the costs of the program but if you
do it in every interaction
it will produce um counterproductive
results so
an exact match for unity 2020 at the
local level would be tough
uh because whereas the presidency does
flip between red and blue
and you know even putting aside for the
moment that red and blue did not mean
what they have in the past
and that many of us who have always
voted blue are fed up with with the
democrats etc
um cities tend to be
stuck in one or the other uh
color as it were they tend to have a
mayoral leader who's of one party or the
other
on and on and on and on and you know i'm
not sure that's as much true as maybe it
used to be but certainly i would be very
i i don't know and we haven't been in
portland long enough for me to know most
of my local history very well
but i don't know when the last time
portland had a republican mayor was
right so you know
a unity 2020 exactly mapped onto the
local level might be tougher
but but something that had two people
uh who were to some degree
disagreeing on you know i don't know
eight or ten of the top
issues that are plaguing the city today
uh
running as as a team could be
could be an effective way to bring unity
2020 to a local level
well i think um there's no structural
mechanism because you don't have two
offices you don't have
president there's also that if you if
you had vice mayor
you could potentially do it but we don't
have that but the fact is
unity 2020 or let's just say the unity
movement is really about the recognition
that there is a tension between
values and that far better than having
one side advocate for one value on the
other side advocate for the other value
and the pendulum swing back and forth
between them or
you know that's how it works in the best
of circumstances in our
country uh recently it's done nothing of
the sort but
um you could recognize
that the solution involved navigating
the tension
rather than oscillating between the
extremes
there's no reason you couldn't do that
at the city level and in fact we have
this very tension at the city level
you know business owners and homeowners
for example
have one view of things and uh
renters uh will have a very different
view of things so
you could navigate these things um
in terms of the unity viewpoint the
unity perspective but you just couldn't
structurally do it
so anyway yes i think it is a good idea
for us to figure this out and the unity
movement should
um try to figure out how to map
that uh higher order value set onto
other other power dynamics
since so many big cities increasingly
refuse to pursue charges against
protesters
in quotes what happens if big city cops
just refuse to arrest any
anti-protesters
and then the the question continues
problem solved
probably wouldn't be solved but it might
point to
the problem with not arresting or
pursuing charges against protesters such
that
at least it was revealed to more of the
constituency of a city
well yes on the other hand it's a step
what the protesters rioters are
demanding is effectively
a discretionary legal structure
where there's uh one set of
people for whom the laws apply and
another set for whom they don't apply
it's a reparations program
within that context but the problem is
it breaks down into a totally
discretionary thing
which will be the uninvention of
civilization rather than a solution
you can't balance the discretionary
thing on one side with a discretionary
thing
on the other side there's no stable
solution that looks like that
so um you know yes yes certainly
certainly
it's not a stable solution but could it
be used short term
as a sort of a hail mary to point out uh
just how bad a policy this is well i
expect it to happen
i don't expect it to be deployed but i
expect
um you know i expect you will see
you know look you know who wins out of
all this
the anarchists for a very brief period
of time they're going to get their wish
and um we will be if we are lucky we
will be picking up the pieces for
generations
about how long have humans been evolving
in caves and handmade shelters and how
has that affected our physiology
this could be covered for hours but a
light explanation for you is sufficient
thanks are you much so this is going to
be different
for different populations and i actually
uh i did not go back and try to figure
out when is the oldest
uh cave living that we think there is
evidence for
um although gosh there's some stuff at
the southern tip of south africa that's
very old that i think is millions of
years old that has
evidence like uh shellfish processing
that might be
in a cave so you know caves versus
handmade shelters are are quite
different
uh answers to this question um
and uh but but the question then is
how might this affect our physiology
yeah i don't expect any start date on
caves
um start date is that what you said yeah
yeah i mean other animals use caves
so there's no reason that there's any
human start date that one should
expect but the other thing you know we
had to have come down out of the out of
the trees
we had to have been on the ground
probably yeah you're right there are not
a lot of trees in caves therefore you
could have
but then you have a come down out of the
trees
uh date for early primate ancestors
but it it's not the answer you're
looking for what i would say is if
you're interested in caves i've long
been interested in caves because they
often house
bats you realize that they are so
patchily distributed
that there is no um
you know caves exist in some places and
people will certainly use them because
they provide advantages
caves don't exist in other places people
have
long had mechanisms for doing something
else
let's make nests you know so
that that suggests that behavior that
you could call a man-made structure
stretches back before our split from
chimpanzees
structure and shelter differently
there's there's lots of mammals and
birds and
even some amphibians and reptiles that
make nests
but shelter and cave you know what what
i read as
underlying this question is are there
going to be effects on
say ability to regulate to
thermoregulate
or photo period interpretation
if you're living if you're sleeping
inside a structure that either
mitigates changes in environment such as
temperature
and rain and protects you
which may mostly be a negative from the
direct evidence of the sun and the moon
moving throughout through the sky
and because it's been so um
so varied throughout human history i
doubt that we could find any
consistent physiological change as a
result of this
certainly at the point that the vast
majority of people are living inside
we should expect to see changes in our
ability to acclimate that would be
harder
and harder for any of us to you know go
out and spend time
outdoors for for lengths of time uh but
that's probably at the level of
individual acclimation rather than
long-term evolutionary uh change
i would think yeah i mean i think the
the problem is it's
it's almost a continuous uh state of
being change
where um you know at first a cave
is basically just a place where the rock
overhangs enough
so that the rain doesn't fall so some
space stays dry and you seek shelter
there
which reduces your caloric needs because
you don't get wet and because you don't
get wet you're not
losing the uh the energy you're
producing by burning
food calories um and then you know at
some point caves get deeper people don't
typically
move really deep into caves unless they
have a good reason to do it because it
just complicates everything
um and you know likewise the shelters
that people build at first
are much closer you know they don't
insulate you from the photo period
issue so anyway
i think the point is the impacts are
much more likely the much
the later you go in those technologies
okay last question from episode 39
before we finally get to the ones from
this
hour last hour rather i recently bought
a bunch of eggs
labels coming from free-range chickens
and all 10 of them had double yolks
what could possibly explain this
chernobyl 2020
yoke loneliness love from kiev
so the kiev part is is relevant because
he posits chernobyl as a possible
explanation
which would presumably not be an
explanation unless every time you buy
free range eggs you're getting double
yolks
anything well one thing is you have to
guard against
the the fact is double yolked eggs
are not all that uncommon
um so there's a question about how
unexpected
any seems very unexpected if you know
if it was a completely random process
that produced double yolked eggs
then you would expect for each you know
if you get one double yolk tag what's
the chances that the next one
uh is also double yolked would be the
same percentage and you
multiply these and you get a very low
overall percentage well but i mean it
might be just like in humans some
families have propensity towards
twinning
yeah right and so some chickens
presumably have a propensity towards
double yolking
yep and so free-range chickens
uh may be more likely to be being
produced on smaller farms and so the
chances of having a small farm in which
a majority of the chickens are actually
have this tendency towards double
yolking
would be higher than if it was coming
from some giant farm um so that's you
know just
just you know basically drift towards
double yokiness
in free range eggs is is possible
because you're talking about likely a
smaller population that you're pulling
from
yeah so i what i was going to get at is
the individual likelihoods if they were
all multiplied together
seem very low you can't rule it out
somebody's going to get just by chance
somebody's going to get that
carton at some point and maybe they'll
write to somebody and ask a question
about it
on the other hand a free range doesn't
mean what we
think right free range is an appeal to
some idealized
version of uh you know chickens
chickens going their own way whatever it
is
but anyway so the thing is
these chickens they go somewhere to lay
their eggs you know there's some
nest box and uh somebody's you know your
life if
one chicken has a propensity to lay
double yolked eggs they're very likely
to end up in the same place they're very
likely to be collected at the same time
so
basically the point is non-independence
of yolk points that's good
okay excellent um you were saying in a
stream
that two-thirds of one's ancestors being
women is a misunderstanding of
individual versus population
that it's actually one in two yes
and i do not understand the second the
actual question here
but maybe you will brett isn't this a
contradiction since two to the n
spots in one's tree will cover whole
subpopulations
in the limit i think there's
there's some there's some illusion i
mean two to the n
is obviously mathematical it's exponents
but i don't understand what we'll cover
a whole subpopulations in the limit
it's referring to it yeah you know i
understand this is a mathematical term
but i don't quite get how it's being
used here
do you understand
i don't yeah so maybe we could just say
again
um although probably we'll just say the
same thing as we said whenever it was
that we said that that
um this thing that has tried it out a
lot that oh you know um
women make up many more of your
ancestors than men do
misunderstands that even if you come
from a population where there is a lot
of
polygeny which is to say one male mating
with a lot of women and a lot of males
not leaving any descendants at all
that is true at the population level but
every individual human being has one
father and one mother
and therefore absent incest which yes
can happen but even in strongly
pollutionist societies
is is pretty rare um absent incest you
have an equal number of male and female
ancestors
yeah so i think the point is
this two-thirds number if the two-thirds
number is right it does point to
something important
right about mating systems in human
history about mating systems in human
history and the bottle
the routine bottlenecking of men yes
um so that's a very real thing and i
think it's important the problem is the
way it's deployed is often very
confusing
and so anyway it's not like we're saying
it's a non-existent
it's a false idea and so so like we just
don't know if the two-thirds number is
right but let's imagine for the moment
that two-thirds is the right number here
what we're saying is that
um two-thirds or some such uh
number is true with regard to the
population at some moment
in history had uh two-thirds
boy i don't even know how to say it for
the population level um i can't do it
with
i don't want to do it such that i can
get clipped out of context because i'm
just not sure this number is right
it is true that uh at a population level
at many moments in human history
many more women than men have reproduced
it is not true that at any moment in
human history
any individuals have many more female
than male ancestors
that's what is true yep
escaping the matrix that told me
evolution was a lie from satan
and that the universe is 6 000 years old
was rather hellish
i need a respite do you have any
suggestions to escape the madness of men
and fall back in love with nature
i'm willing to travel and i have money
oh boy
yeah so many suggestions yeah i don't
know about i don't know if any of them
work right now
right i mean if you're an american uh
you're not allowed to travel except to a
few caribbean islands and mexico as long
as you fly
um and i guess you know ecuador if
you're willing to do a 14 day quarantine
but most of the world is off limits so
assuming you're willing to wait a little
bit
so many wonderful suggestions for nature
um
one of our favorites is well all of
ecuador really but the ecuador and
amazon
and yeah we could we could just list and
list a list do you have any just off the
top of your head
um yeah
here's the i think the real answer is
it's everywhere
right and if if you can't see it then
there's a scale at which you could
and so anyway we have a um
a thing that a shorthand we say to each
other about the fact
that uh creatures elsewhere that are
very exotic to us
may be their squirrel that we have
squirrels that we take for granted and
actually
squirrels are completely fascinating
creatures they're behaviorally just out
of this world
highly intelligent problem-solving and
uh
amazing to watch and there's some places
you can go you could sit all day and
watch squirrels and nobody would know
what you were doing but
um but it's worthwhile and we just
ignore them because they're so
commonplace
this is i mean this is absolutely true
and you you can do
you can learn a tremendous amount and
immerse yourself in animal behavior
almost anywhere
uh but in terms of getting a respite of
actually getting away you know going
into the back country
and the us is is still available i think
i think even
even backcountry even national parks
were shut down for a while but i think
almost all of them are open again
um if you know at your own risk so if
you have
if you had the skills to do that for
that you need skills that money won't
money won't solve your problems
um you know don't don't go somewhere
if you really want a respite and escape
from the madness of men as you say
do not go somewhere that has been
americanized in advance for you
which is you know it's the way most
americans tend to travel and
any place that has uh that is a giant
tourist destination for americans
i'm assuming you're american and if i'm
wrong then this is this is going to be
slightly different
but any giant tourist destination like
for instance
you know cancun or acapulco or cabo san
lucas
uh is just going to be like many america
except the climate's a little bit
different and other people around you
are speaking
in spanish although frankly probably not
even that much
so go somewhere that a bunch of
americans aren't already swarming to
at the point that americans are once
again swarming places
and um not just immerse in nature but
also engage with the local people
and that is actually a cure for the
sense that
uh the madness of humanity you know the
madding crowd is everywhere
um it's it is so eye-opening to just
interact with people in of a different
culture
in a different language even if you only
have a few words but you can actually
communicate quite a lot and then
you know we've spent time we spent time
in turkey i don't know that when
when that is going to be safe again but
um cappadocia in turkey is extraordinary
uh you know madagascar is is really
difficult
in a lot of ways but um unlike any place
else on
earth and there's so many places in
latin america
uh that are distinct um and
just gorgeous with regard to to nature
um one that springs to mind on the
southeast coast of the yucatan
near the belize border in mexico is lake
bakalar where we spent some time
a few years ago um really quite
remarkable
yep there the snail kites are like
squirrels the snail cats are like
squirrels
yeah it's like squirrels i would say one
thing to be aware of though
is there is this empty forest phenomenon
where places that are intact with
respect to plants
are not intact with respect to animals
for various reasons
hunting can do this very easily so you
want to be
sure that you're either not
traveling to some place that
looks good superficially and some eco
lodge is
going to try to satisfy your desire
in order to get you to spend your money
sometimes you have to work to get to
some place
that's far enough away from people
that nature is still intact there
otherwise you get a very wrong message
about
how common the animal
life is yeah
could you please clear up if unity 2020
is still possible
there are a few posts going around the
unity forums putting on their black hats
and saying it is mathematically
impossible
is this true no mathematically
impossible no
i will say it grows less likely with the
absence of a groundswell and to be
honest with you
lots of people who go around saying it's
impossible are making the ground swell
unlikely in and of itself so they're
sabotaging unity and at some point
i expect many of them to be very sorry
they did that because
what's going to unfold in the absence of
a unity ticket
is going to be a disaster it's
guaranteed and
people you know people at some point if
they're smart will
remember that there was another
possibility and that they bypassed it
for
uh basically reasons of
short-sightedness at best
if not cynicism you know what's what's
the risk right like this is the thing i
don't understand is what
what is the risk that people are
perceiving uh to trying it out
and seeing seeing if
it might make sense and just holding out
hope
right so i will say um this
mathematically impossible business
is entirely predicated on the idea that
the plan
was to get on ballots by collecting
signatures which that was never the plan
we knew that wasn't going to work
in the very beginning if that had been
the only mechanism
then we would never have embarked on
this
it would it would have been unity 2024
right like that's
right exactly um so you know
there are other mechanisms and it is not
mathematically impossible it does get
harder there are various points at which
of the many mechanisms one drops out and
so
you know it becomes less likely at a
structural level
but you know if events intervened at
this moment yeah it's still possible
sure
how does your oh no here we go
shouldn't the corporate backing of the
blm movement demonstrate to the left
the practical benefits of free market
capitalism while also alerting the right
to its potential dangers
balance is necessary much love to all
yeah if we were all in a learning mode i
think that's you know that's that's apt
right
that this this could be a way for both
sides
to learn from to learn about their own
blind spots yeah
absolutely um increasingly i think it's
really important
that we get careful around the idea of
capitalism as either a savior or a
villain
that you know i don't i don't know what
people mean
by capitalism if they just mean markets
then they're talking nonsense
because first of all then they're
talking nonsense when uh
when they say they're anti-capitalists
anti-capitalist yes yes we're going to
destroy all markets really forever like
or until
five minutes from now as if markets you
know haven't been with us
since the you know the first moments of
exchange
right it's like oh i mean i can make an
argument that other organisms besides
humans engage in markets of course
and so the thing is it's a little bit
like you know the uh
the cave and shelter thing right which
is you know it starts with such a small
alteration that you can't even identify
a point on the other hand there's
clearly
something about the um the markets that
we have
now that left to their own devices do a
tremendous amount of harm
but you know i really just think we
should turn the question
back on people like what exactly is it
that you want to end
right because there's no they don't know
they don't know what they're talking
about
and the thing is if you are interested
in something that would actually deserve
the label
social justice then markets are your
best
tool right what you need is a market
that is
in a context where the incentives result
in more just outcomes then the market
finds the solution rather than
ibram ex candy inventing a solution
that's going to result in the
destruction of civilization
right but collecting his share oh he
he's a marvelous capitalist
yes yeah how does your conception of
geographical and transfer frontiers
apply to the rest of the natural world
i can see how the dynamics of the
geographical frontier could be similar
but cannot intuitively apply transfer
frontiers
so this actually fits perfectly with the
previous question
so you know what um in what way could we
argue that
other organisms besides humans engage in
in markets
or in exchange that looks like markets
uh you know just
famously to use the one that that
titillates is sex for food trades within
bonobos right
the so-called pygmy chimps sister tax on
to chimps uh and when and you know and
and so-called nuptial gifts
are present from you know spiders and
wasps and you know all
all over the animal kingdom in which in
order to get access
uh usually to a female a male must
supply a gift of some sort usually food
sometimes his own
body and and that is
that's a kind of market right that is an
exchange uh that is not
a for a but a for b and uh there's going
to be constant negotiation between
each player in terms of whether or not
they think they're getting
a good deal and no it's not conscience
conscious when it spiders and
to some degree some of it's going to be
in bonobo some of it will be conscious
but not as fully conscious as it is in
humans and of course a lot of the trades
that we do aren't conscious and we think
because we use language we put this
conscious wording on things
and um then we forget all the stuff
that's happening below the surface
because we think our words are our
truths and they're not
yeah um i agree with this and one of the
reasons
that um we talk about mating and dating
markets is that this really isn't
conscious people are involved in
uh market-like exchanges even when
they're
they find that terminology abhorrent but
somebody who
is versed in the technolo and the
terminology can just map it on there
very very easily but here's the thing
you know you've got lots of examples
that we can find uh within
humans in places that we don't expect it
within other creatures
in close context like uh you know
bonobos within their group and all
but if you're willing to look between
species
the stuff is everywhere right every
one of these insect or animal pollinated
systems
fruit distribution you know creatures or
even
oh so so so what you're talking about is
you know a bee comes to a flower
and gets uh gets nectar and exchange
carries gametes to the next flower so
clear trade but even something like
mixed foraging flocks
of different bird species one of whom is
helping find the food and the other of
whom is better at
alerting against predators like that's a
kind of exchange as well oh of course
and you know frankly if you and i were
to just set about the
task we could probably
come up with example after example until
we literally
fell asleep at the microphone because
you don't want to see that
no you don't yeah um no and
market forces will prevent us from doing
that because it wouldn't be a good
strategy
however i mean look we've got
even just you right you are
yeah you all are you um you are
um simultaneously an
individual and a
colony of gut flora and you know other
creatures that live yeah some of them
are eating right now
well not anymore um but uh you know
your gut flora are part of a partnership
in which they get something
and um you very definitely get something
the ability to live because of their
activity in
your gut and even even your cells
your cells are um
the composite of two distinct creatures
right your mitochondria were at one
point free living creatures who took up
residence
inside of cells that became eukaryotic
so you're not even
one creature you're a partnership at the
level of 30 trillion cells each of which
have these uh
little once autonomous creatures within
them
uh you know we've got networks of um
fungi that allow plants to
um uh extract nutrients
from their soil environment and there's
an exchange of resources there
the exchanges are everywhere and
um anyway a little imagination reveals
just how
broad a concept it is yeah so i think um
we
we did not actually answer the question
what was the question which was about
transfer frontiers oh and where we see
transfer frontiers
in in non-humans and i think basically
anytime
uh you see theft of resource or uh which
often manifests as territoriality um
that's
that's effectively a kind of transfer
frontier you know we're talking within
species
um well gosh not even like i can think
of just from
from my own research i had i had one
frog species moving in and stealing
stealing a place in which to rear his
his babies from another frog species
and once done there was no using that
resource again until the second frog
species had raised his kids and moved on
yep so nectar thieves nectar thieves
oh yeah hummingbirds that go in at the
base of the flower rather than going in
where they're supposed to and so get the
nectar but don't pollinate
absolutely they're beautiful but they're
diabolical yes nasty nasty hummingbirds
i'm a big fan of hummingbirds but yes
they do all sorts of creatures
steel and in fact i have bad news for
you
animals we're stuck with it all right we
we are not autotrophic right and even
those you might
be thinking but corals are autotrophic
no they're not because they
might need to define your terms uh
generating their own food so plants are
generating
uh carbohydrate from sunlight and co2
in the atmosphere they're literally
taking air
and turning it into sugar and cellulose
using
energy from the sun like that's the
honest way to do it so autotrophic
self-feeding effectively versus
heterotrophic other feeding which is
what we are
yeah so basically no matter what kind of
animal you are you're stealing
those uh resources from some
animal or some plant and ultimately if
you chase things
these things down far enough it has to
come from some autotroph almost all of
which are plants
which are generating these things
through photosynthesis so you know
um do we still call it a transfer
frontier
if it's been going on for so long that
it's just the way things function
you know it's kind of a distinction
without a difference
but anyway uh is it a perfect match
maybe not maybe uh maybe it's just
easier when you're talking about human
populations but it you know if you
back off the tolerances just slightly at
maps
very well yep
okay we're gonna get through a few more
of these because we spent a long time on
the four that
weren't even from this last hour uh
hoping you can share some evolutionary
thoughts on recreational substance use
are we faced with new stressors and
lifestyles that are prompting new ways
to cope
or have we always looked for ways to
alter consciousness
uh yes the answer to both of those
questions
um so in part uh create a world of
stress from which you cannot escape and
in which
boredom also reigns uh
reigns supreme and you will not only
have uh people or rats where research
has been done
um seeking to press the lever for more
cocaine or whatever it is over and over
again but they're more likely to become
addicted
when they're bored and uh that's that is
that is just now well understood
um put aside that addiction and
um you know abuse as opposed to use have
we
uh boy where is the question have we
always looked for ways to alter
consciousness
absolutely i believe
i don't think it's a universal because
there's just a lot of little cultures
that we don't have complete information
on
but this is one of the things that seems
close to a universal
in the human experience that there is
the seeking of some kind of altered
consciousness
um from you know something as simple as
fermenting fruit
uh to bringing together a number of
amazonian species
and making ayahuasca yep um yeah it's a
brain hack uh that allows you to
do various things i would argue it
allows you to to
uh move across the standard lines of
consciousness so that you're basically
investigating
your own um hidden cognition
but anyway people do it with all sorts
of stuff that isn't you know even
substance based sometimes like uh
sweat lodges for example yeah and
uh starvation and anyway there's all
sorts of stuff
um so yes it's a it's a long-standing
tradition in so many cultures
that you'd have to be crazy to imagine
it was anything other than
adaptive which isn't to say that every
interaction is adaptive right
are there examples in biology of
predators that hunt by disguising
themselves as prey
how effective are they compared to other
types of predators thank you for the
informative content
just let me say there's lots of evidence
lots of examples of prey disguising
itself as something that's toxic or
dangerous
yeah episomatic prey but um there are
some
very handsome deep-sea
fish oh god that have a
yes like a little uh looks like an
invertebrate
on a fishing anglerfish anglerfish
speaking
hesitant to say anglerfish because i
know that anglerfish
is a term that applies to some amazonian
fish
is that oh those are archer fish maybe
yeah i think those are archer fish
um that shoot insects off of yeah
i think this thing attached to the yeah
i think you're right the deep-sea ones
are angler fish
um and uh anyway they're very they're
very interesting creatures yeah um
also they're actually so handsome they
are very lovely yeah um
no actually they are basically um
it is not true but it should be true
that they had to descend so deep in the
ocean that there was no sunlight on
account of
just sheer ugliness there's a bat like
this as i remember that has a it's so
good that he has a flap but he pulls up
over his face
yeah yes i'll show a picture we will we
will show that
he's a very interesting fruit bath yeah
but not pretty nope
not pretty um did we answer that
question
oh yes yes we did oh how effective are
they compared to other types of
predators
i don't so the only example we came up
with anglerfish i don't know
in order to answer the question how
effective are they compared to other
types of predators you really want to
compare
control for both phylogeny and ecology
and i don't know who the english fish
are related to
and i don't know if they're deep sea and
so it it's
likely that such fish have gone into a
new place
and therefore it's going to be
impossible to answer the question while
controlling for the things you would
have to control for
yeah i don't think i don't think it's an
answerable question yeah that's right
and i will say i'm coming up with other
examples now like when i think about oh
there was this thing
i i tweeted about it some years back uh
a spider mimic at the tail on the tail
of a
snake that causes birds to birds that
eat spiders to come and then get eaten
by the snake
exactly um and then i had a couple more
oh there are some others kind of like
that i think snakes snakes may do stuff
with their tails
that it's not it's not exactly uh
well they're disguising parts of
themselves as prey yeah there is stuff
like this
that definitely yeah yeah yeah um and
then there's other stuff like um
you know looking blending in with a
flower which is kind of at the edge of
your question
right if you if you're a like a a mantid
disguised as a flower part and some
pollinator is going to come to pollinate
the flower it's not exactly what you're
talking about but it's really close
i mean camouflage is that's why i say
it's at the edge because
they're camouflaging themselves as
something that
indicates food yeah so i think it counts
thematically but it's not a perfect
match
in gender ideology they say that
everyone has a gender identity
cis peoples matches their sex but they
can't explain what gender identity is
can't measure it and it doesn't have a
material basis do you have thoughts
yeah gender ideology is uh
ideology that is a decent match for a
lot of the modern
woke anti-analytical anti-scientific
ideology
it's impossible to assess impossible to
falsify um
that said as i you know as we've said
now many many times
here and elsewhere gender is real it's
not a human construct it wasn't made up
by humans gender is
the behavioral manifestation of sex and
for some people looking around at what
the dominant
way that members of their sex tend to
behave they may say you know what i'm
gonna
i'm gonna prefer to behave like the
other sex or in stereotyped ways they're
more like
the other sex behaves like that's that's
fine you know behavior doesn't have a
material basis
but um you know not having a material
basis does not render it
uh unfalsifiable or untestable or
unscientific
it's the point where they wiggle out of
all attempts to figure out what they're
actually talking about
that makes it unscientific there's a lot
more but
i mean you know at some point we're just
going to get down to
can we just be decent to each other
right the idea that we're going to
establish this category it's not on the
basis of something scientific so we're
going to assert that it is and then
we're going to bend the science to make
it seem scientific
look you know gender is interesting it's
highly plastic it has certain consistent
features there do seem to be
some people who are um
out of phase with their uh
morphology such that trans is the right
category and that appears to be an
ancient phenomenon
but not nearly at the level that we are
seeing it nor
does it suggest that surgery is the
proper response that you know so anyway
i think i think we just need to be
decent to each other and uh
leave open the possibility that there's
stuff we don't get but at some level
there's an awful lot that we do get and
it does not match the
madness that we are seeing yeah okay
we'll do three more here and then we'll
switch to the next
to today to this hour's livestream
um i'm not sure what this next one means
next time you're on rogan can you
explain to him that 10 to 20
of mongolian men being direct mail-line
descendants of genghis khan
means that 100 percent are direct
descendants in some fashion
i'm not sure why that is posited as a
as a truth i i think the point
is that if 10 to 20 percent of mongolian
men
are direct mail-line descendants
above some threshold then a hundred
percent of them
are likely to be descendants below some
threshold that the nature of
genes as this self-atomizing
property over time means
that
you have to set a threshold to establish
so the idea is that that 10 to 20 is
what we can discern with our current
tools
and because what we can discern with our
current tools
is uh is imprecise and we're going back
in history a long ways
right so if you set some threshold where
you say you need
uh x level of sequence identity right
in order to be able to say descendant
then well what
what percentage would you come up with
if you had half that level
and then there's a point at which it's
so low
that you can't establish it but it
doesn't mean it's not there it doesn't
mean you don't have
uh genghis khan somewhere
in by some ancestor i guess so yeah
so i guess um
however he's talking about men and
and it feels it seems to me that you can
trace the y chromosome
and um you know direct descendants of
genghis khan
should all have his y chromosome
and that that shouldn't have slop in it
there will be uh some inaccuracy in the
test
but it's not going to get less
concentrated over time it's just it's a
y chromosome and there's not a lot even
crossing over at that 23rd
uh 23rd spot
i am now afraid that i'm about to make a
serious error that i will be
correcting with great embarrassment in
the next live stream but it doesn't seem
to me
that a direct descendant of genghis khan
necessarily has to have his y chromosome
direct male descendant
well direct male descendant does not
mean
oh okay so you don't we're not talking
about a line of male male male male male
right so
um his daughter could have had a son
there um that doesn't have his white
chromosome so i'm not wrong no you're
not you know
you're not wrong um so yeah so the
direct
if i mean maybe maybe this recovers the
question then yeah
um it's not the 10 to 20 of mongolian
men being direct male line descendants
it's
10 if if what is hidden in this question
is that 10 to 20
of mongolian men are understood to be
direct mail line descendants because
they have
his y chromosome and therefore we know
that male male male
male male male yeah then there's a whole
lot of other stuff going on
every time bingo i think we got it yeah
yeah
and again because with this obviously
strongly pledging to society there would
have been a lot of daughters
that didn't have of his that didn't have
his why that then went on to produce
uh boys yeah yep okay good
man is venosaur who answers that
question
uh two more here and um
or what did i say two three something
like that did you happen to read the
atlantic article
anti-racist arguments are tearing people
apart maybe the author saw your latest
live stream
ha reassuring that the periodical isn't
100 in on the candy kool-aid yeah oops
oh god what just happened
what happened um here just put my screen
up for a second zach i actually
believe it or not had this open and
thought we might get to it
in the first hour and didn't um but yeah
so this is conor friedersdorf it's not
too surprising that he ended up writing
this piece
but the fact that he's still published
in the atlantic is a good sign
there you go um according to the u.s
census
male atheists outnumber females female
atheists in a two to one proportion
why do you think it is this way please
uh i think this is going to have to do
with um this is going to be a similar
answer to why
women can form at higher rates uh when
you
put them through like the ash conformity
experiments and such
and that are more interested in
appeasing
and soothing over
disruption and discomfort on average
as a rule uh than men are and at the
moment
and presumably forever atheism is
a is a minority view it's a fringe view
and it doesn't offer the kind of
community or comfort that
religion does yeah are to say it's
slightly differently
um males are traditionally
more likely to uh blaze new
paths and the path out of an established
belief system
is likely to be pioneered by males more
frequently than females
i don't think there's any reason to
expect that that pattern has to continue
just that it has traditionally been male
associated
behaviors and that one of the things i
mean but but it's been male-associated
behaviors for the same reason that
in every human culture that does whale
hunting
women don't do whale hunting right so i
mean it's it's
it is in part about um not being able
you know if in your prime you might be
pregnant
or or breastfeeding um you're less
likely to be taking huge risks that
would put not just you
but your tiny children at risk yeah
i see some aspect of that because this
is completely a
belief which doesn't necessarily mean
atheism or atheism a simple belief it
seems to me that there is a
this is probably not going to make sense
to people but
you could there is no bar
to writing new mental code that couples
atheism with exactly the same
behaviors that would emerge from faith
or some particular faith there's no bar
you can write any code you want the
software level
so what that means is if it is true
that the beliefs that are resident
inside these evolved
systems is resulting in behavior that is
necessary for
females to carry out the part of their
role that would block them from taking
up whale hunting
that code could be generated and
therefore
you can break the pattern um
that said well i guess the plea i would
make one more time
is we are at a place where we have to
renegotiate
the um relationship between males and
females the ancestral stuff
doesn't work and the no holds barred
everything is post-modern doesn't work
either
so what we need to do is figure out how
to renegotiate this so that everybody
has
access to whatever it is they want to do
but nobody is
forced to take up stuff they don't want
to do because of some naive belief that
we should all want the identical
and i don't know
i mean you and i have done this it's
possible
um and so i think it's important that
people just recognize that there is a
mechanism to do it and it will not be
that it can be a very positive thing but
it is not a simple matter of saying
anything that ever created a gender role
distinction
was oppressive and you can't um
you can't cheat you can't say i don't
want any of the downside of this gender
role but i want all the upside
yeah neither neither neither sex is
allowed to do that and um
what has been pointed out
it is captured the third wave on later
feminism
uh is that it would appear to be too
often exactly that a desire to keep all
of the upside
uh that comes from being a sex that
warranted protection
and did not have to take the risks while
also claiming all of the upside
of the other sex you can't you can't
have it both ways
yeah yeah all right we are
switching now to the questions from this
hour
oh scrolling could there be a role to
play for an antifa version of titania
mcgrath
uh never calling for violence but giving
high resolution satire of antifa
positions
james lindsay thinks it's too dangerous
what do you two think
that's from the militant moderate
james lindsay thinks is too dangerous um
look at this point we are on a
trajectory
for the collapse of the basic
functionality of civilization
at some level i don't know what too
dangerous means
because it's slated for destruction so
um could it make things worse um of
course
a lot of that is always the risk with
anything
uh that is novel but
at some level when you're headed for the
waterfall
right you got to figure out what your
best likelihood is of paddling out of
the current so that you don't go over it
well i guess the the way it could be too
dangerous more than what titanium
mcgrath is actually doing is that the
titanium mcgrath
character uh is making outlandish claims
and you know calling for sort of social
cancellation yep right but antifa
actually regularly um calls for violence
and so what would a what would a
titanium mcgrath style
uh parody of antifa look like
if it was to be believed if it was to be
effective that didn't also sometimes
call for violence and therefore
wouldn't it be potentially dangerous and
that it might result in
same yeah i get it um i mean
obviously it can't uh you can't do it
as titanium mcgrath does it i don't know
you know the funny thing is i would have
to go back and look at what titania
mcgrath does
um because it seems to me that it
involves the same danger
but it is well done yeah in other words
you can't do it haphazardly you have to
do it in such a way that the parody is
very very clear and i don't know what
you do in a world
where you know well but uh so i can't i
can't remember
i'm sorry i can't remember the name of
the british comic who is actually
titania mcgrath
um but he was doing her character for a
while without it being clear that it was
a character
and that was a large part of its
effectiveness and then he got outed by
someone on the woke side who thought
that would cancel
mcgrath and it didn't like the character
continues to be quite powerful although
i think the account was taken down
briefly on twitter recently
that's not how i remember it it was he
was anonymous
it wasn't known who titania mcgrath was
but it was a clear
parody from the beginning i think i mean
certainly it was clear to some of us
right well i guess i mean that's that's
where it is then right
yeah um tim dillon did a great parody of
antifa in the hamptons
okay that sounds it sounds hilarious
uh bandanas have been pooh-poohed by the
media recently as an effective mask
compared to other options
do we need to hang up our spurs
um it's a good question i saw this the
methodology
was atrocious which doesn't mean that
the conclusion
was wrong but my thought was first of
all
i will make an argument for bandanas on
the basis
that they solve one of the problems that
masks
in general cause which is because they
can't be integrated normally
into what you wear they are inherently
oppressive whereas
if i put on my bandana
and i go out into the world i don't even
know it's there until i'm suddenly about
to go in someplace that i need to have a
mask and it's already on me
so my thought was if bandanas are
actually less effective they weren't
ineffective but they were less effective
in the particular study you're
referencing
then there's a question about what would
you have to make them out of or what
would you have to line them with that
that was no longer the case and really
we should be shooting just as people
have produced lots of masks that have
humorous things on them or
designs that are nice or whatever we
should be making bandanas
that solve the problem by changing the
pore size if that's the
issue and that retain the value of it
which is that you can just simply have
it on and not think about it
and go into the world and you know i
actually find
in at least two instances that the mask
has come in handy even in places
where i didn't need one the bandana or
the
basket the bandana yeah so i had this
experience
i was riding down a bike path
uh in a forest around here and there
were bugs
um and i pulled up the mask and i could
breathe
over your helmet uh i wasn't wearing a
full face helmet i was oh yeah
um and then the other place was
leaf blowing i kicked up a ton of pollen
and
i was already wearing a dust mask so
anyway um
yes there's a question to be answered uh
to the extent that that
atrociously um arranged study
is actually indicating something real
which i'm not convinced that it is
but if it is then the question is well
what do you have to do to modify it
because the design
beats the hell out of wearing a mask
over your ears and pulling it down under
your chin which looks ridiculous
isn't comfortable causes acne i hold it
in my hands when i'm not wearing it but
it's not a great solution it's not a
great solution so anyway i
ultimately the answer is let's come up
with a great solution that integrates
with your life doesn't make you feel
self-conscious
doesn't cause acne is there when you
need it all those things and
works really well yeah
bretton heather do you what are your
favorite movies also this contribution
isn't for you
it's for your cat thank you he is very
much appreciative we will buy him fancy
steaks
actually we won't we'll buy us fancy
steaks and we will let him smell them
um he'll get the the the grisly part
yeah he does and he likes it
um i actually wrote that i saw this
question was coming and i wrote it down
to uh answer it next time because i have
some strange
lapse in memory that whenever i'm asked
a question like that i immediately
forget all movies that ever existed or
books or any such thing i agree it's a
difficult one yeah um
yeah we have uh i'm
so i i promise we'll come back to it if
you want to just pass this for now
yeah i'll give you one okay i'll give
you once you have something to
watch in the meantime i can do shows
worries of the movies at this point
frankly because we've been watching some
of their kids
yeah indeed brazil is a great
movie oh also the big short
big short if you have a certain
orientation to the world the big short
is
a really um emotional movie
as yeah the renegades are fighting
the the mockery and the insistence of
their
bettors that they are uh seeing a mirage
yeah anyway those are both good yeah
actually i'll provide a show
um that we recently uh re-watched
maybe my favorite um which is peaky
blinders which is just
just extraordinarily well done yeah that
is a great show
apparently this next question is
supposed to start with the words
that should make more sense oh yes that
will make it make more sense thank you
zach
do primates perceive emotion better in
the left visual field right hemisphere
baboons hold opponents on their left
side do we tend to move anti-clockwise
enclosed spaces
for instance stores to be ready for
danger on the left
that is fascinating echo um
i don't i don't know um
i don't i don't know if the question
about
other primates is known um
i would be surprised if we had if if we
had shifted that from
um other primates to humans like what
would have explained us
flipping the directionality of um
emotion in terms of the lateralization
of brain hemispheres
as i would think would be similar but of
course there's emotional processing
in both in both hemispheres um and then
this question about moving
anti-clockwise and closed spaces stores
i'd never thought of it but as soon as i
read it i started imagining
i thought well they're they're all set
up that way isn't that just because like
we're just forced to do it but no
they're they're all set up that way
no they're not anticlockwise they're
clockwise but only when viewed from
below
ah um
yeah this is a tough one for one thing i
think the real
i don't know the answer to this question
but i do think the way to think about it
is if it were the case
that we reduce our vulnerability to
enemies by keeping them on a predictable
side in which we better process their
intent or whatever it is
then there would be a premium on being
the enemy
that didn't work this way but worked the
opposite way
which is i mean almost certainly you
know it's the adaptive explanation for
you know not just handedness but there
being a nine-to-one ratio
of right-to-left-handers in every human
population right so that having
you know having the dominant way being
useful for sort of group cohesion and
problem solving but always having
someone in the group
um that is likely to be thinking about
what about attacks from that side or
maybe i can lift i can get up into the
tree that way or whatever it is
well but the problem is that i'm
wondering
if the logic in this case so you know
if you take the example of the the
desirable object in the tree
that isn't accessible with the right
hand but is accessible with the left
hand so that the group gets or
the lineage gets accessed to it by
virtue of having
a lefty um and you don't need an even
number but in the case of this
antagonism idea i'm wondering if it
doesn't tend to a 50 50.
where to the extent that there is a
strong bias
towards one side the advantage to coming
from the other side
is great until you get to 50 50. and so
i'm doubtful about this in an
antagonistic context because i think you
would get to
a 50 50 parody or very close to it
unless there was some other reason for
the lateralization
um so i'm doubtful but i i wouldn't rule
it out
what is your view on the impact on the
lack of techno-optimists
recently all mainstream technology and
science themes have been overwhelmingly
dystopic
do we need a new wells haldane julian
huxley etc
do you understand i don't quite get
the connection so i would i have
i in the past have argued that
techno-optimism is part of the problem
that we are facing that it's a kind of a
new cornucopianism that imagines
um that all we need is human ingenuity
to solve even problems
of clear resource depletion um
which you know resources are finite and
zero sum
and no amount of human ingenuity can can
change
that fact um
it is true though that dystopian views
of the future
are much more common at least in sort of
my my sense of what kinds of stories are
are making sense right now
uh than than optimistic ones and i don't
want to use the word utopian because
that's
less likely you know a dystopia is going
to be easy to fall into and a utopia
just won't happen so how about an
optimistic version
i guess an optimistic version of a
future that doesn't put too much faith
in
technology and human ingenuity is what
i'd be looking for
so i think i think this question doesn't
quite
insofar as i know exactly what's being
asked doesn't doesn't quite thread the
needle
exactly the way that i would do so yeah
i think
what i see going on is our system
is so techno-optimist by
structural design that the nature of
markets of our political
apparatus the corruption of our
political apparatus all of these things
tend towards techno-optimism right that
is to say
um where we might have the precautionary
principle
or the chesterton's fence recognition of
old protections and things like that
what we instead have
is this childlike faith that that which
is new
is fine until we know better right at
which point it's too late to do anything
about it
and so i guess the point is i think the
dystopian nature of our fiction
is the natural outgrowth of a system
that is based on the faith of the safety
of the novel
the novel is not safe and
because we are on a uh
on a ship that is committed to the idea
that it is safe until proven otherwise
we are headed to dystopia right we are
um
blindly headed into the north atlantic
in the winter
at breakneck pace on the basis that most
patches of water are not uh
inhabited by an iceberg yeah right which
will result in you hitting an iceberg
soon enough okay we are going to try to
get through
uh
looks like six more uh very quickly
one of these is just a comment a google
search for brett weinstein listed you as
an american biologist
his search for eric listed him as
brett's brother from one younger brother
to another congratulations
well i would imagine that would dismay
aaron just read this to toby as well
eric is certainly listed
as a an american mathematician oh for
sure but he's just
yeah he absolutely is but occasionally
having the younger brother
uh show up as the the main guy as
opposed to
the older brother always taking first
totally although i'd be
i'd be heartened if it was like uh
you know brett's older and slightly
dimmer brother or something
like that yeah that'd be cool now you
would you would not like that actually
okay following oh yeah so following up
from five weeks ago well both of you
interview
at richard hartwin who has been
demonized by bad actors and smear
campaigns for eight months
uh we have not looked into this i don't
actually remember this
um we get a lot and you know i will
actually zach can you i think i
i think i'm actually aware of this
person slightly i want to make sure that
it's the same
account um so brett says he might be
aware of him i will say that we've been
getting a number of
requests for people um to be featured on
darkhorse with brett
um and uh really too many to
uh to even give much thought to
to many of them but uh that said we do
appreciate
we do appreciate it and might might look
into it
my wife daughter and i are huge fans of
you both my wife is due with our baby
in two weeks we would love to hear your
thoughts on circumcision as we both have
differing opinions and neither of us is
very staunch thanks
so you did this recently yeah you
answered this
maybe two two episodes ago and i think
uh dave
our the guy who's making the clips for
us actually clipped it out so
we might just refer to that yeah the
short version is
the foreskin and circumcision are both
adaptive that's the implication
of the fact that the foreskin exists and
it is made of material and therefore
passes the adaptive test but the removal
of it also passes the adaptive test
so probably these are responses to two
different selective forces that are in
tension
the question is how does this map on to
modernity
in other words if for example the
removal of the foreskin is
a uh a an issue of hygiene
and epidemiology as has sometimes been
implicated
to very much um
this has been controversial but
nonetheless if
that's what the removal is about then it
is possible that modern
medicine or um the access to
reliable um hygiene maintenance
mechanisms like showers and things
means that that advantage no longer
applies don't know but
you're you're dealing with something
that existed for a purpose in the past
and it is unclear how it maps onto the
present
my sense is
that that probably means that you are
free to navigate this that you know
there's costs and benefits on both sides
and
do what feels right i don't think
there's a terrible
mistake to be made and i will just say
that um
lest people misunderstand as i suspect
people did when you talked about
circumcision a couple
weeks ago just because something has
persisted and been adapted for a
population does not mean that the rest
of us need to look at
and applaud it or get behind it you know
this is this
this is a long-standing argument in
cultural anthropology right you go in
and simply observe even things that
that you yourself find heinous if you
were trying to do ethnography
or are you allowed to speak what you
understand to be
a better a better way so
for instance often
people who are simply critics of male
circumcision will say
well if you are in favor of it you must
also be in favor of female genital
mutilation
and really uh there there is no good
analogy between those
two things in part because although we
don't know as you have said brett
what the adaptive reasons for male
circumcision have been where they have
shown up multiple times in human history
there has never been a suspicion or a
hypothesis that has gotten
anywhere with evidence that it was about
controlling
um reproduction of or you know otherwise
controlling the demographic that is men
whereas female genital mutilation
clearly has been about controlling the
sexuality
and the demographic that is women and
whenever you are controlling a
particular demographic
uh with something that is widespread it
may well have been adapted but that
doesn't mean that it's any less
cruel unreasonable heartless and should
be abandoned
yeah um one final note i would just say
there are many mechanisms whereby a
human mating system has been maintained
almost always the downsides of those
maintenance mechanisms fall
on women which is not fair um that said
the west which basically abandons this
invites a whole different level of
catastrophe of a different sort
and so we need to discuss those things
in the context
of each other right right so it's at the
moment what it is is pick your failure
mode
and the real question is how can we
avoid a failure mode and share the costs
of whatever our system is equally that
would be the ideal
yeah okay two more questions
one of which is a double
uh or actually it's just a two-part
thing first first of two
the death metric really bothers me i try
and explain it this way
hypothetically if the virus took 20
years off the end of life
old people would die middle-aged
unhealthy people would be at risk
young adults would be mostly fine kids
would have almost no deaths
do you still want your kid getting this
thoughts on the percentage graph to you
thoughts on the percentage graph do you
give long-term effects on heart
brain lungs reproduction so that's more
of a comment than a question but i think
it's a really apt
you're thinking of it exactly right and
whether it really is that it knocks 20
years off the end of life or not it's
probably more complicated than that but
that's
certainly how we should be thinking
about it it's a good simple rubric and
that's before we even get to the
question about whether
or not it may be in people who have
recovered
hiding out in neurological tissue to
re-emerge
later the way um uh herpes zoster which
is chickenpox
hides and then comes out and causes
shingles so
we're really early days here with
respect to what the actual cost of this
thing might be
yeah and the fact that it doesn't show
up in you know
immediate death is little comfort given
how many systems it damages and how
severely it apparently does so
yeah okay last question for today
i was watching a documentary on tantra
tantric sex with colombian girlfriend
many affluent white women gyrating and
moaning to connect with their sensuality
the girlfriend asks why don't they just
dance is dance adaptive
what are the effects of dance losing
popularity in the white west
this is a great question yeah and yeah
your colombian girlfriend asking why
don't they just dance
that is apt that is that is terrific
yeah in fact uh for years now i've had a
plan
to have a podcast discussion with iona
italia about this very
question about what is lost in the
tradition of partner dancing because
even if you have dancing
so she does tango exactly exactly and so
yes i think there are great many things
that are supposed to be worked out on a
dance floor that
um get worked out in other much more
destructive
ways and we you know it's another one of
these things where
um it's it's it's uh um
chesterton's nightlife well let's see
you came back
um at one of your long field seasons in
panama you had um
in order to keep the visa alive uh you
had gone to cartagena for a few days
right uh with a bunch of other people
from from stri from smithsonian tropical
research institute where you were
working
and you reported in fact you would i
think bought a piece of art that then
got lost in transit somehow that i never
saw but i still
have this image in my head of this piece
of art that you had that i haven't seen
of a couple dancing um either salsa or
morenga i don't remember maybe if it was
colombia it wasn't either of those but
some laughs
okay um in which uh
and you said that it reflected some of
what you'd seen in cartagena as well in
panama too but i remember you talking
about cartagena it's just a place i
haven't been so maybe i'm
romanticizing it unlike the other places
you talk about
yeah i so i hear um but it was this
oil painting of a couple in tight
embrace
both of whom were quite heavy set and
neither of whom were young
but both of whom were beautiful and
doing the dance well
and clearly engaging in sensuality and
and frankly sexuality in a way that was
totally acceptable and lovely and loving
and wonderful
and that this was also something you
were seeing among people dancing
actually yeah and uh anyway
it's too much discussion for this late
in our podcast but
there's a whole landscape that needs to
be sorted out here because
it isn't that dance is sex it's not
but it is related in some way that has a
lot
it touches on a great many different
parameters and the fact that the west is
so confused about this
is in part because um you know
i don't think people in cultures where
couple dancing is an important
feature necessarily have the meaning of
it
explicit in their minds right it's just
something one does but
you know the fact that you're you know
if you go to a disco
in latin america right there's a lot of
modern music that
your grandmother wouldn't recognize but
your grandmother's music also shows up
too
yeah and when it does people are more
likely to partner up in partner dancing
and prediction those cultures that still
have
a fair amount of partner dancing that's
done by young people have a lower rate
of people succumbing to gender ideology
yeah right
exactly all right all right
um well yeah so so
so all right um
yeah again uh find us on our patreons
for
private q a once a month on mine the
discord
uh server is available through either of
them there is a clips channel
that will have clips from today's stream
up within a few days
and subscribe to this channel if you
want notifications
uh turn on notifications what else
uh you know uh achieve awesomeness
oh definitely rock on all of those
things rock on
yeah all right thanks folks and we'll
see you next time